《第一滴血》
你能告诉我贝瑞是否住这里?
Can you tell me, does Delmar Barry live here?
不好意思  你能告诉我  这里是贝瑞的住所吗?
Excuse me, Can you tell me, is this where Delmar Barry lives?
他不在
He ain't here.
进屋内去  宝贝
Go on inside, baby,
他是我的好朋友
He's a friend of mine,
事实上  他写下这个地址
As a matter of fact, he wrote this address down,
这里
Right here.
你可以看出是他的笔迹
There. As you can see, that's Delmar's writing,
这地方真难找
I sure had a hard time finding this place,
是他的笔迹
That's his writing.
我说过他是我朋友
Like I said, he's a friend,
我叫蓝波  越战时我们服役同部队
My name is John Rambo, We served on the same team together in Nam.
我不知他是否提过我
I don't know if he ever talked about me,
我有一张我们合照的照片
I've got a picture of us together,
在某个地方...
Somewhere,
口袋乱七八糟的
This junk in my pocket,
在这里
Here it is, Here it is,
这是我  这是丹波  还有维斯伍
That's me, That's Danforth, and Westmore,
朗森  欧太加  还有贝瑞站在后排
Bronson, Drtega, and there's Delmar right in the back,
他个子大  得站后排
We had to put him in the back 'cause he's so big.
否则无法全拍进去
If we didn't, he'd take up the whole picture,
瞧瞧他的大块头
Look how big he is.
贝瑞离开了
Delmar's gone.
他何时回来?
Oh, What time will he be back?
他死了
He died,
什么?
What?
去年夏天死了
He died last summer.
怎么死的?
Died. How?
死于癌症  在越南得的
Cancer, Brought it back from Nam.
他们到处喷化学药剂
All that orange stuff they spreaded around.
让他变成了皮包骨
Cut him down to nothing,
连我都可以把他从床单上抱起
I could lift him off the sheet,
我很难过
I'm very sorry,
早安  安妮 你们好吗?
Morning, Annie, How you doing, girls?
- 很好  谢谢  - 今早还好吧?
- Great, Thanks, - You all right this morning?
- 安笛  - 好  威尔
- Andy! - Howdy, Will.
- 早安  戴夫  - 好  警长
- Morning, Dave,  - Hi, sheriff,
这周去温泉泡澡吗?
Gonna take a bath this week?
早安
Morning,
你来这里拜访什么人吗?
You, uh, you visiting somebody around here?
没有
No.
看你夹克上绣的国旗
You know, wearing that flag on that jacket,
和你的德行
looking the way you do,
你是来这里找麻烦的  朋友
you're asking for trouble around here, friend,
- 北上还是南下?  - 北上
- Headed north or south?  - North.
上车
Ah, jump in,
我一定让你走对方向
I'll make sure you're heading the right direction, hmm?
- 你要去那里?  - 波特兰
- Where you headed?  - Portland.
那是在南边  你刚才说要北上
Portland is south.  You said you were headed north,
这附近有地方可以让我吃东西吗?
You got someplace I can eat around here?
公路上三十里外有家餐馆
There's a diner about 30 miles up the highway.
我在此地吃东西犯什么法吗?
Is there any law against me getting something here?
有  犯着我
Yeah, Me.
你为何逼人太甚?
Why are you pushing me?
你说什么?
What did you say?
你为何逼人太甚?  我没招惹你
I said, why are you pushing me?  I haven't done anything to you.
首先这里轮不到你发问  我做主  明白吗?
You don't ask the questions around here, I do. You understand?
第二
Secondly,
本镇不要你这种家伙
we don't want guys like you in this town,
流浪汉
Drifters.
你得知道
First thing you know,
因为我们镇上有很多你的同类  这就是原因
we got a whole bunch of guys like you in this town. That's why.
而且  你不会喜欢这里
Besides, you wouldn't like it here,
这是个平静的小镇
This is, this is a quiet, little town,
事实上  可以说是乏味
In fact, you might say it's boring,
但是我们就喜欢这样
But that's the way we like it.
我拿薪水就是要维持这样
And I get paid to keep it that way,
乏味
Boring,
波特兰  一直向前就到了
Portland, straight ahead,
给你个友善的建议
Now if you want some friendly advice,
去洗个澡剪个头发
get a haircut and take a bath,
就不会惹这么多麻烦
You wouldn't get hassled so much,
希望送你这一程对你有帮助
Hope this ride helped you out.
祝你有愉快的一天
You have a nice day, hmm?
该死的  你想去那里?
Where the hell do you think you're going?
我在跟你说话  可恶
Hey, I' m talking to you, goddamn.
身分证件给我看  该死的
Let me see some ID, Damn it!
好  你被逮捕了  听见没有?
You're under arrest, You hear me?
手放车上
Put your hands on the car.
手放车上  双手打开
Now you put your hands on the car and you spread 'em.
你要把手放车上
Now you're gonna put your hands on that car,
你要怎么做  自己决定  现在!
How you do it, you decide. Right now!
腿向后伸
Get your legs back,
腿向后!
Get 'em back!
乖一点
You know, you try to be nice to some people.
这是什么?
Well, what do we have here, huh?
你为何会带这种刀?
Why would you be carrying a knife like this?
- 打猎  - 少自作聪明
- Hunting. - Don't be a wise guy.
你用这把刀猎什么?
What do you hunt with a knife?
说
Name it,
- 威尔  - 莱斯特
- Hi, Will, - Lester,
把他收押下去好吗?
Buzz us in, will ya?
说曹操  曹操到
Talk about your sorry-looking humanity,
只是另一个自作聪明的流浪汉
Just another smart-ass drifter.
早安  阿舍
Good morning, Arthur.
早安  威尔  你抓到什么了?
Morning, Will, What do ya got?
我要以流浪拒捕
I want you to book this gentleman for vagrancy,
携带武器  的罪名拘捕他
resisting arrest, carrying a concealed weapon,
他说他用它打猎
He says he uses it for hunting.
打猎?  你猎什么?  大象?
Hunting? What do you hunt? Elephants?
把他弄干净点
Why don't you see if you can clean him up.
闻起来像野兽
He smells like an animal
- 麦屈?  麦屈?  - 在
- Hey, Mitch? Mitch? - Yo.
- 护送这位小伙子下搂  - 好
- Escort this young man downstairs, would ya?  - Yes, sir.
走这边  伙计
Right this way, partner,
这边  对
Right here. That's it.
好  走吧!
Okay, Here we go,
看来李洛要
You know, it looks like it's going to take ol' Leroy,
十年才能漆好这走道
about ten years to paint this hall,
李洛  手脚快点
Leroy, sling that paint,
沃德先生?
Mr. Ward?
- 把这把枪收起来好吗?  - 谢谢
- Would you take this for me, please?  - Thank you,
好
Yeah.
姓名?
Name?
你的姓名?
Your name?
姓名?
Name?
你想找麻烦?
Hey, if you're looking for trouble,
你来对地方了  伙计
you came to the right place, buddy.
等一下
Wait a second,
给你三秒  然后我会打碎你的脸
Hey, you got three seconds before I break your face in,
他是说真的
He means it,
对
Yeah. I do,
你知道吗?  亨利是阿兵哥
What do you know about that? OI' Harry here's a soldier,
蓝波  强尼  J?
Rambo, John J,?
你会跟我说话的
You gonna talk to me,
我保证你会的
I promise you're gonna talk to me, soldier,
我开始不喜欢你了
I'm starting to dislike you,
很不喜欢
a lot!
我要查他的资料
I'm gonna run a make on him,
把他的名字输入电脑
Put his name in the Teletype,
放过去
Now just roll it across.
放...放过去
Roll it, Roll it across.
- 用力压  - 行不通的  只会弄坏
- Push it.  - It won't work that way. It'll only smear,
- 放过去！  - 听着  你这狗娘养的
- Now roll it across!  - Look, you son of a bitch,
你不把你该死的手放上去
if you don't put your goddamn hand down there,
我就打断你的手  放上去  该死的！
I'm going to break it off. Now, put it down, goddamn it!
这里在做什么?
Art, what the hell is going on down here?
没有我处理不了的事
Oh, nothing I can't handle.
他不让我们好好按指纹  威尔
He won't let us print him, Will,
别碰纸
Leave the ink on the hand!
你有什么毛病?
Just what is your problem, huh?
听着!  难缠的家伙  你目前的罪
Now, listen, hard ass, as things stand right now,
要坐九十天牢和250元罚钱
you're facing the ass end of a 90-day incarceration, plus a $250 fine,
我看你付不出来
which you don't look to me like you can pay.
明早十点
At 10:00 tomorrow morning,
你要站在法官面前
you're going up in front of that judge.
你以为我们难缠?
And you think we're tough,
我们要让你明天出庭时
Now we're going to make you a little bit more presentable
更像样点
for your courtroom appearance.
在那之前  别让我更讨厌你
And between now and then, you can just impress the hell out of me.
照我说的做
By doing exactly as you're told.
把他弄干净
Now clean him up,
好  布莱斯
All right, Preston,
我要你去把水管准备好
I want you to go over there and get that hose ready,
明白了吗?
All right?
看那个!
Holy shit! Look at this,
- 他遭遇过什么事?  - 谁在乎?
- What the hell 's he been into?  - Who gives a shit?
手放头上  转过身去
All right, put your hands on top of your head and turn around,
天啊!
Oh, Christ!
我们该向提索报告这事  高尔  看看!
We should report this to Teasle, Galt. Look at that,
你照我的话作就对了
You just do what I tell ya.
高尔  这算那门子?
Galt, what the fuck was that?
威尔说要把他弄干净
Well, the man said clean 'em up.
弄干净
Clean him up.
布莱斯
Hey, Preston,
别忘了洗耳朵后面
don't forget to get him behind the ears!
你喜欢吗?
How do you like that, huh?
怎么了   麦屈?
What's the matter, Mitch?
不喜欢水上运动?
Don't you like water sports?
好  快点  我的休息时间到了
Hurry it up. It's time for my coffee break,
- 坐下  - 快  坐下
- Sit down  - Easy, Sit down,
坐下  好  坐在椅子上
Sit down. All right, Sit on the stool
快点
Come on,
可恶  真难制住他
Damn! Damn, this boy's hard to get ahold of.
看护 别管洗面乳了  他很强硬
Ward, don't worry about the soap, He's tough,
- 刮下去就对了  - 好
- Just shave him, dry  - All right,
你看不见吗?  看不出他疯了吗?
How blind are you? Can't you see this guy's crazy?
- 你不明白我不做无聊的事?  - 我看得出
- Can't you see I don't give a shit?  - Yeah, I can see that,
好  好多了
Good, that's better,
我就知道他会听话
See there, I knew he knew what was good for him.
我只是替你刮毛  伙计  放轻松
Just gonna shave you, partner. Take it easy,
拿着这个  麦屈
Take this, Mitch.
别动
Don't move,
我不希望你害自己的颈子被割断
I don't want you to cut your own throat.
你这混帐
You son of a bitch!
来啊!
Come on!
把他拉走  把他拉走
Get him off of me!
到底怎么...?
What the hell is...
阿舍? 阿舍?
Art? Art?
你不可以...
Hey, you can't...
等等  等等
Hey, hey, wait a minute...
我要射他
I'm gonna get that son of bitch!
阿舍  别射
Art, don't shoot!
可恶!  别射  那边有人
Goddamn it! Don't shoot, There's people down there,
去求援  我去追他
Get help, I'll go after him,
让开!  小心!
Move!  Look out!
让路!
Get out of the way!
狗娘养的!
Son of a bitch!
莱斯特  我是威尔  我正在追他
Lester, this is Will. I'm right on his tail
他现在在史密斯农场东侧  往查普曼溪前去
He's just east of Smith's farm, headed towards Chapman Creek.
我知道你可以听见我的话
I know you can hear me!
你完了
You're finished!
你逃不了多远了!
You've gone as far as you're gonna go!
你听到没有?
You hear me?
麦屈!  莱斯特!
Mitch! Lester!
他在山岭上
He's up there, beyond the draw.
麦屈  用无线电呼叫奥佛
Mitch, get Orval on the radio.
叫他立刻带狗来这里
Tell him to get out here with his damn dogs right away,
叫他带杜宾犬来
And tell him to bring the Dobermans,
快下雨了  我们需要那些能依视觉追猎的狗
It's gonna rain. We'll need dogs that can hunt on sight,
好！
Right!
叫高尔到集木场
Lester, tell Galt to get out to the lumber camp.
- 叫他带直升机来  - 好
- Tell him to get the helicopter up here.  - Right.
他们抱怨
If they give him any shit,
就叫妨碍公务逮捕!
tell him to cite them for obstruction right on the spot!
我们会抓到他  没问题
We'll get him, No problem,
快点  狗儿  打猎开始了
Come on, Duke, Thunder, Let's get him,
加油!  甜心  就这样宝贝
Come on, sweethearts, That's it, babies.
去抓他
Let's go get him!
很快就可以抓到他了吧?
We'll be done in a couple of hours.
你很快就可以把他剥制成标本了  是吧  威尔?
It won't be long before you have this one stuffed and mounted, huh, Will?
我们去年来这里猎过鹿吧?
Didrt we go deer hunting here last year?
对  去年我猎到些公鹿
Yeah. I got a couple bucks.
- 现在要射杀他  - 麦屈  在山顶
- I'll shoot anything,  - Hey, Mitch, up the hill,
别让它们接近我  奥佛
Keep those dogs away from me, Orval
我不信任它们
I don't trust those bastards,
继续跑  我的狗可以边跑边吃
Keep moving, 'cause my dogs can eat and run at the same time,
他准备上山顶
He's heading straight for the top,
- 这人可能有危险吗?  - 他完蛋了
- Is this guy supposed to be dangerous?  - He's just dumb.
小心  你破坏他的气味了
Hey, Walt, you're spoiling the scent,
- 让我的狗去追  - 去吧
- Let my babies do the job.  - Go ahead.
我在这跟着你
I'm trailing you here.
- 没有用  - 为什么?
- This is no good,  - Why?
当时在搂下我们有三个人对付他
There were three of us on him in the cell block.
他闯出去如入无人之境
He went through us like we werert even there.
少来!
Aw, come on.
快走  狗儿  快点
Let's go, babies, Come on, Duke,
好
Hey, hey. Okay, Thunder.
快点  我们困住他了
Come on, Duke, We got him cornered,
阿舍  这是提索  他在往查普曼峡谷走
Art, this is Teasle, He's headed for Chapman Gorge.
查普曼峡谷  去追他
Chapman Gorge, Head him off.
他在那  悬崖上!
There he is! On the cliff!
狗娘养的!
Son of a bitch!
怎么回事?
What the hell 's going on?
你干什么?  我们应该只是看住他
What are you doing? We're just supposed to spot him.
保持稳定
Hold it steady,
我不能  我们在乱流中
I can't! We're in a thermal draft.
他困在那边  那里也去不了
Galt, he's stuck there, He can't go anyplace,
要是你不好好开直升机
If you don't fly this thing right,
我向天发誓  我会收拾你
I swear to God, I'm gonna kill you.
警长呼叫高尔
Sheriff to Galt.
保持稳定  你狗娘养的!
Hold it steady, you son of a bitch!
高尔  回答!  可恶!
Galt, come in, goddamn it!
靠近点  保持稳定
Get in closer and hold it steady.
高尔  跟我说话  我要知道究竟怎么回事!
Galt, talk to me. I want to know what's going on!
我打中他了  慢点
I got him, Easy. Easy.
天啊!
Dw! Jesus!
他在那边
There he is!
到那边去  快!
He's over there, dummy. Come on!
快!
Go on!
阿兵哥!
Hey, soldier boy!
接近点  他在那边
Move it, move it down the side.
保持稳定!
Hold it steady!
快!
Come on!
高尔  我叫你听无线电!  怎么回事?
Galt, get on this radio! What's going on up there?
我要知道怎么回事  听见没有
I want him alive, Galt! You hear me?
高尔  回答
Art, come in!
小心
Watch out!
阿舍!高尔!回答!  直升机回答!  该死的!
Art Galt, come in, Helicopter, come in, goddamn it!
天啊!  看!
Jesus Christ! Look!
天啊!  拿望远镜给我
Jesus Christ, Give me the binoculars, hurry.
不  不  糟了
Dh, no, no, no, Shit!
天啊
Jesus Christ.
我想不透
I can't figure it.
他怎么摔出去的?
How'd he fall out?
这不重要
Does it matter?
他几乎打中那小子  他逃不远
Let's nail this sucker's ass, He can't be far.
威尔!
Will!
看来他想自首
Looks like he wants to turn himself in,
死了一个人
There's one man dead!
不是我的错  我不要再有人受伤!
It's not my fault! I don't want any more hurt!
别动!
Freeze!
站在原地别动  投降
Stand right where you are! Give yourself up!
但我什么也没做!
But I didn't do anything!
我警告你  别动  否则打死你
Boy, don't make a move! I'll blow your head off!
我什么也没做!
I didn't do anything!
停火!  停火!
Cease fire! Cease fire!
可恶  停火!
Ward, goddamn it, cease fire!
我想我们打中他了
I think we hit him.
我们下去  快!
Let's get down there, Move!
警长呼叫基地  请回答
Sheriff to base. Come in.
说吧!  威尔
Go ahead, Will,
莱斯特  我们现在在峡谷底
Lester, we're down in the gorge,
高尔死了  直升机在那里?
Galt 's dead all right, Where the hell is that goddamn chopper?
他不来  他说有暴风雨朝你的方向去
He won't come, Will, Says there's a storm headed your way,
我不管有什么来
I don't give a goddamn what's on its way!
我要直升机快来
I want that chopper back here right now!
我不要高尔的尸体停在这里整夜
I don't want Galt 's body out here all night.
我尽力而为
I'll do what I can.
威尔  你真会挑人找麻烦
Will, you picked one hell of a guy to mess around with.
刚才电脑输出资料
This came over the Teletype.
蓝波是越战退伍军人
John Rambo is a Vietnam vet.
绿扁帽特战队成员
He's a Green Beret.
得过国会勋章  他是战斗英雄
Congressional Medal of Honor. Guy's a war hero.
天啊  他?
Jesus, that freak?
我就知道他有来头
I knew there was something about that guy,
我会再查一次  威尔
I double-checked it, Will.
你要我做什么?
What do you want me to do?
我要你照我刚才说的话做  该死!
I want you to do what I told you to do, goddamn it!
叫直升机现在回来!  完毕!
Get that chopper back here now! Out!
绿扁帽  战斗英雄
Green Beret. War hero.
这可好了
That's great,
- 真是好了  - 闭上嘴
- That's just great.  - Why don't you shut your mouth?
你们怎么了?
Now what the hell 's the matter with you guys?
他只是一个人  而且受了伤
He's one man. He's wounded,
那些绿扁帽真的不好惹
Those Green Berets, they're real bad asses,
你何不让州警处理这事?
Why don't you let the state police handle this?
过来  该死
Come here, boy, Come here, goddamn it!
看着他  看着他  他是阿舍高尔
Look, look at him, look at him! It's Art Galt, boy,
你妈替你擦鼻子时我们就是朋友
He and I were friends when your mama was still wiping your nose!
现在他死了  他因为山上那疯子而死
Now he'd dead, He's dead because of that psycho out there!
你听好  我要抓到那混帐
You listen to me, boy, I'm gonna get that son of a bitch.
我要把他的国会勋章钉在他肝上
And I'm gonna pin that Congressional Medal of Honor to his liver,
有没有你帮忙  我都会做
And I'm gonna do it with you or without you,
我脚扭到了
Dang! Twisted my ankle!
我们接近他了  味道愈来愈浓
We're closing in. The scent's getting stronger.
好  睁大你的眼睛
All right, keep your eyes open.
快点  宝贝
Come on, baby,
暴风雨要来了  那是目前最需要的
It's gonna storm. That's all we need now.
威尔  在天太黑之前  我们快离开
Will, let' s get out of here before it gets too dark.
怎么了?  你怕鬼?
What's the matter? Are you afraid of the bogeyman?
你这娘娘腔
You goddamn pansy,
沃德  放下枪  我让你看看谁是娘娘腔
Ward, put your gun down. I'll show you who the pansy is.
来啊!  来啊!
Okay, come on down!
伙计们  住手!
Hey, guys, knock it off!
沃德  继续走!  战斗在那边
Ward, move on! The fight is out there!
他在等着你们!
He's out there waiting for you!
麦屈  站起来  走!
Mitch, get on your feet and move!
去找那家伙
Let's go find this guy for Christ's sake!
- 睁大眼睛看着!  - 这边  杜克!
- Keep your eyes open!  - Come on there, Duke!
回头见  沃德!
I'll see you later, Ward!
闭嘴  麦屈!
Shut up, Mitch!
我们走  快
Let's go, girl, Come on.
他在那边!
There he is!
放开那些狗
Turn them loose! Turn those dogs loose, Drval!
去收拾他  甜心!  享受你们的晚餐吧
Go get 'em, sweethearts!  There's your dinner!
停火!  停火!
Cease fire! Cease fire!
我中弹了  该死  我中弹了!
I'm hit! Goddamn it, I'm hit!
天啊  他有枪!
Jesus. He's got a gun,
那不是他  是稻草人
It's not him! It's a goddamn scarecrow!
稻草人不会开枪  他在附近  很近
It was no scarecrow that shot Drval! He's close, real close!
杀了他  杀了他  快去抓他!
Kill 'im! Kill 'im! Go get 'im! Go get 'im!
去收拾他  麦屈!
Go get 'im, Mitch!
麦屈!
Mitch!
麦屈  沃德  过来
Mitch, Ward, come here,
- 席格  你掩护我们  - 看他的脚
- Shingleton, you cover us.  - Look at his leg,
麦屈  用你的皮带  绑他的腿
Mitch, get your belt. Get a tourniquet around that,
我们必须送他去看医生
We gotta get a doctor!
该死!  快拿皮带来
Goddamn it! Get your belt on there fast!
- 急救箱在那里?  - 我把它留在车上
- Where's the first aid kit?  - I left it in the car,
- 可恶!  - 他从那里弄到枪?
- Shit!  - Where'd he get the gun?
阿舍高尔的枪
It's got to be Art Galt 's gun.
- 他没弹药了  - 你怎么知道?
- He's out of ammo.  - How do you know that?
杀死最后只狗的不是子弹
Because whatever killed that last dog was no bullet!
这就是原因  快点!
That's how. Hurry up!
奥佛  听着  你待在这里
Orval, listen to me, You got to stay awake,
每十五分钟松开皮带
You got to release that tourniquet every 15 minutes.
我们马上回来!
We'll be right back!
我们要去抓他  他没子弹了
We got to get him now. He's out of ammo.
- 抓他!  快点!  - 他竟然射杀了我的宝贝
- Hurry up! Get him,  - He had no right to shoot my babies,
- 抓那混蛋!  - 快  我们走!
- Get the son of a bitch! Go get him!  - Come on! Let's go!
好  现在  听好
All right, All right. Now, listen up,
我们己包围他  我们要组成间隔50尺的前哨线
We're right on top of him, We're gonna form a skirmish line 50 feet apart.
别停下来  除了闯过我们  这里别无出路
And keep moving, There's no way out of here except through us,
好!  我们来打猎吧!
Okay, Let's do some hunting,
打猎?
Hunting?
不是我们猎他  是他猎我们
We ain't hunting him. He's hunting us.
分散!  分散!  该死!
Spread out! Spread out, damn it!
我说是50尺
I said 50 feet!
该死!
Dw! Damn!
天啊  我真讨厌这事!
God, I hate this!
天啊!
Ow! God!
- 威尔!  是麦屈  - 可恶  威尔!
- Will, it's Mitch!  - Oh, shit, Will!
天啊!
Oh, God!
威尔!
Will!
- 是谁?  - 威尔
- Who is it?  - Will!
威尔!
Will!
麦屈?
Mitch?
- 怎么回事?  - 狗娘养...
- What the hell 's going on?  - Son of a...
威尔!
Oh! Will!
他攻击沃德了
He's got Ward,
分散  我走这边
All right, spread out. I'll go this way.
威尔!
Will!
威尔!  威尔!
Will! Oh! Oh! Will!
在这边!
Over here!
威尔  他在那边!
Will! He's over here!
停火!
Hold your fire!
- 谁开枪?  - 我打中他了  我打中他了!
- Who the hell is firing?  - I got him! I got him!
席格  跟我来!
Shingleton, follow me!
我打中他了!
I got him!
来人啊!  救我  救我  威尔!
Somebody help me!  Help me, Will!
- 威尔  - 高佛?
- Will!  - Balford?
- 高佛  你在那里?  - 威尔!
- Balford, where the hell are ya?  - Will!
救命!  救我!
Help! Help me!
高佛?
Balford?
席格  到这边来!
Shingleton, over here!
天啊
God. Jesus.
放轻松  把我弄开  放轻松  好
Easy. Easy. All right. Hold it,
天啊!
Jesus Christ!
席格  你在那里?
Shingleton, where the hell are ya?
席格?
Shingleton?
威尔!
Will!
天啊!
Jesus Christ!
天...
Jesus...
我本可以杀光他们
I could 've killed them all.
还有你
I could have killed you,
镇上你称霸  山中我为王
In town, you're the law, But here, it's me.
别逼我!
Don't push it!
别逼我!  否则我会让你痛不欲生
Don't push it, or I'll give you a war you won't believe.
就此罢休!
Let it go!
好  退后
All right, Coming in,
- 快点  退后  - 退后  伙计们  退后
- Come on. Get back,  - Move back, you guys, Move back,
长官  我们需要聊聊  发生什么事?
Captain, can we have a comment on what's happening?
状况有多糟?  长官  我们需要...
How bad is the situation? Captain, we need some...
这件事
Only good thing to come out of this mess,
只对镇上生意有好处
Is the business we're doing in town.
记者把酒都喝光了
Reporters are drinking the place dry.
你看起来疲倦不堪  威尔
You look like you're ready to keel over, Will.
何不回家去?  现在我的问题了
Why don't you go home? It's my problem now.
你的?  听好  戴夫
Your problem? Listen, Dave,
少跟我谈这案子的管辖权
don't give me any of your horseshit about jurisdiction on this one,
知道吗?
you understand?
要我出去吗?
Would you like me to step outside?
做完你的事就对了
Just finish up what you're doing,
在此岩山荒野某处
Somewhere in this rugged mountain countryside,
可能在雪线上的薄雾之中
possibly above the snow line, shrouded in mist,
藏着亡命的退伍军人蓝波
the fugitive John Rambo is hiding.
州警与当地国民军
Units of the state police, along with local members of the National Guard,
正动员起来
Are now being mobilized,
当地警方仍未解释的是
What still remains unexplained by local authorities,
这前绿扁帽从何处以及如何
Is just how and where the former Green Beret,
得到武器
Came into possession of the weapons with which
他杀死了一位副警长
he allegedly killed one deputy sheriff.
并企图杀死其他六位警员
And tried to kill six others.
但他们的警署特训技能救了他们的命
Only their skilled training in police enforcement techniques saved their lives.
逃亡被逮捕只是时间问题了
Word is that the fugitive will be in custody in a matter of hours,
地图给你  威尔
Here's the maps, Will,
威尔  我认为你应该知道一件事
Will, there's something I think you ought to know.
等会儿再跟你谈
Talk to you later. Okay?
是什么?  莱斯特!  说出来!
What is it, Lester? What is it? Spit it out!
我  我跟麦屈谈过
Well, I was, I was just talking to Mitch,
他说高尔和几位副警长
and he was saying that Galt and a couple deputies.
虐待那家伙
Were, uh, a little hard on the guy,
混帐!
Assholes!
这有差别吗?  戴夫
Doesrt make one goddamn bit of difference, Dave,
你心里有数!
and you know it!
若我的副警长
Look, if one of my deputies,
对犯人太过分
Gets out of line with a prisoner,
犯人应该来找我!
then the prisoner comes to me with it!
若我发现他说的属实  我会惩罚副警长
If I find out it's like he says, I kick the deputy's ass!
我!  依法行事!  事情就应该这样办!
Me! The law! That's the way it's got to be!
大家都犯法
People start fuckir around with the law.
那不天下大乱?
And all hell breaks loose!
上帝怎么会创造蓝波这种人
Whatever possessed God in heaven to make a man like Rambo?
他不是上帝创造的
God didn't make Rambo.
- 是我创造他  - 你是谁?
- I made him.  - Who the hell are you?
山姆  崔普曼  崔普曼上校
Sam Trautman, Colonel Samuel Trautman.
今早我们有点忙  有什么我能效劳的吗?
We're a little busy, Colonel. What can I do for you?
我来接我的部下
I've come to get my boy.
你的部下?
Your boy?
我征召他  训练他
I recruited him,  I trained him.
我在越南指挥他三年
I commanded him in Vietnam for three years.
所以我说他是我的部下
I'd say that makes him mine
我纳闷国防部
I wonder why the Pentagon would
为何派上校办此事
send a full-bird Colonel down here to handle this.
军方认为我也许帮得上忙
The Army thought I might be able to help,
我不知道以什么方法
I don't know in what way,
蓝波现在是平民  他是我的问题
Rambo's a civilian now. He's my problem,
我不认为你了解
I don't think you understand.
我不是来此从你手中救蓝波
I didn't come here to rescue Rambo from you,
而是从他手中救你
I came here to rescue you from him,
我们感谢你的关怀
Well, we all appreciate your concern, Colonel.
我们会很小心  上校
I will try to be extra careful
- 他让你们生还我真惊奇  - 是吗?
- I'm just amazed that he allowed any of your posse to live.  - Is that right?
坦白说  他失手了
Strictly speaking, he slipped up.
- 你还活着算你走运  - 这可好了
- You're lucky to be breathing.  - That's just great!
上校  你来此检查你的机器为何失灵
Colonel, you came out here to find out why one of your machines blew a gasket.
你不承认
You don't seem to want to accept the fact
你们是在跟游击战专家交手这个事实
that you're dealing with an expert in guerrilla warfare.
他不但善于刀枪  更是赤手空拳的高手
With a man who's the best,with guns, with knives, with his bare hands.
他被训练成视痛苦为无物
A man who's been trained to ignore pain,
无视天气  在野外求生
ignore weather,to live off the land,
会吃连山羊都吃不下的东西
to eat things that would make a billy goat puke,
他在越南的任务是暗杀敌军人员
In Vietnam, his job was to dispose of enemy personnel
杀戮  终结生命
To kill. Period,
一点点消磨取胜
Win by attrition,
他是个中顶尖高手
Well, Rambo was the best,
好  上校  你吓死我们了
Okay, Colonel, you got us all scared to death.
那你和特战部队
What do you and the Special Forces
认为我该如何对付你的疯子?
think I ought to do about your psycho out there?
- 放他走  - 什么
- Let him go.  - Do what?
只是目前
For now.
解除一切状况和他的危险性
Diffuse the whole situation. Diffuse him.
提供间隙让他溜走
Provide a little gap and let him slip through it.
再全国性通缉
Then put out a nationwide APB.
几星期后会在西雅图或者其他地方抓到他
In a couple of weeks, you'll pick him up in Seattle or someplace,
他会在洗车场工作
working in a car wash,
不会有战斗  没人会受伤
There'll be no fight, Nobody else will get hurt.
我的工作我自己做
I do my own work,
我不会放弃  把希望放在他会在西雅图被抓
I won't close my eyes and hope he gets picked up in Seattle.
若你派你的人去他们会送命
If you send your people in there after him, they'll get killed,
我们只是小镇的小派出所
We're just a small, hick town sheriff's department,
但我们和那位特战部队英雄一样
but we're expected to do our duty.
都被人期望尽到职责
Just like our heroes in the Special Forces,
我们在特战部队教他们
In Special Forces, we teach our people
在执行勤务时保命
to stay alive in the line of duty.
真的?  我可没想到过
I never thought of that.
你要打一场赢不了的战争吗?
You want a war you can't win?
二百个人对付你的人赢不了吗?
Are you telling me that 200 men against your boy is a no-win situation for us?
- 你派他们去别忘了一件事?  - 什么
- You send that many, don't forget one thing.  - What?
提供足够的尸袋
A good supply of body bags.
崔普曼!
Trautman!
我不知道你支持那一边  崔普曼
I don't know which side you're on, Trautman.
我认为你只是来掩饰你的过错
I still think you came out here just to cover your ass,
若你当真想救蓝波  跟我来
But if you're serious about taking Rambo out clean, follow me.
Dang
见鬼
州警呼叫蓝波  请回答
State Police calling John Rambo. Acknowledge.
State Police calling John Rambo. Come in, please. Acknowledge.
若你在听  以下是你的处境
If you're listening, Rambo, here is your situation.
你被包围了  所有出路都被封锁
You are surrounded. Every possible exit has been blocked,
每条公路道路  防火道
Every highway, every road, every firebreak,
你的服役表现
You have our word that your services to your country,
会被列入考虑
will be taken into consideration,
你会接受公平对待
and you will receive fair treatment,
只要回答  我们可以商量一切
Just respond, We can work everything out. Dver.
有结果吗?
Anything?
他拿走我的一位副警长的无线电
He took a radio off of one of my deputies,
他一定在听
Then he has to be listening.
若我是他  我会收听一些情报
If I was in his position, I'd try to pick up information,
- 听别人交谈  - 他当然在听
- Maybe catch some cross talk,  - Of course he's listening.
但他不会说话
But he's not gonna break radio silence,
他不会跟我们通话  也许会跟你  上校!
No, Not for us, But he might do it for you, Colonel
他是你的部下  不是吗?
He's your boy, isn't he?
也许你能说服他投降好救我们命
Maybe you can talk him into sparing all our lives by giving himself up,
我可以试试
I can try.
若你不介意为我们设计他
At least, we'll get a radio fix on his position,
我们可用无线电查到他的位置
if you don't mind setting him up for us,
为你们设计他?
Setting him up for you?
那就像把鸟带到猫面前
It 's like bringing the pigeons to the cat.
狗娘养的
Son of a bitch,
- 谢谢你带人来  - 随时候教  威尔
- Hey, Don, thanks for bringing your people out.  - Any time, Will,
伙计  把杂志拿开认真点  也许机会只有一次
Bobby, put the magazine away, Pay attention. We may only get one crack at this,
连长呼叫乌鸦!  乌鸦请回答!
Covey Leader calling Raven. Come on, Raven.
连长呼叫乌鸦!
Covey Leader calling Raven.
连长呼叫乌鸦!  跟我说话  强尼
Covey Leader to Raven. Talk to me, Johnny.
连长点名  蓝波  麦斯纳  欧太加
Covey Leader to identify Baker Team, Rambo, Messner, Ortega,
卡拉达  乔根森  丹佛贝  瑞克瑞  奥尔
Coletta, Jorgensen, Danforth, Barry, Krackauer,
请回答
Confirm.
我是崔普曼上校
This is Col. Trautman.
跟我说话  强尼!
Talk to me, Johnny.
他们全死了  长官
They're all gone, sir.
是他!  追踪下去
It's him. Get on it.
蓝波  你没事吧?
Rambo, are you all right? Over.
本小队全阵亡了  长官
Baker Team, they're all dead, sir,
贝瑞没死  他生还了
Not Delmar Barry. He made it.
- 他也死了  长官  - 怎么死的?
- Barry's gone too, sir.  - How?
在越南就快死了  他全不知情
Got himself killed in Nam, Didn't even know it,
癌症使他只剩下皮包骨
Cancer ate him down to the bone,
抱歉  我不知道
I'm sorry, I didn't know.
我是仅剩的  长官
I'm the last one, sir,
听到你的声音真好  强尼  好久不见
It's good to hear your voice, Johnny. It's been a long time.
你在此造成一些破坏
Look, John, you've done some damage here,
他们不希望再有麻烦
But they don't want any more trouble,
是他  在西北方 他在西北方
That's it. Northwest. He's northwest.
所以我才来
That's why I've come,
我要去你那边  带你离开
I'm gonna come in there and fly you the hell out.
只有你和我  我们一起解决这事
Just you and me. We'll work this thing out together.
够公平了
Is that fair enough?
- 你从哪里来  长官?  - 布莱登堡
- Where'd you come from, sir?  - Bragg.
我试图找你  但他们不知去那找你
I tried to reach you, but the guys at Bragg never knew where to find you,
最近我很少待在布莱登堡
I haven't been spending much time there lately.
他们把我调到华府  坐办公桌
They've got me down in D.C. I'm shining a seat with my ass.
但愿我现在回到布莱登堡
I wish I was back at Bragg now,
- 你出来后我们再谈这事  - 我办不到
- We'll talk about that when you come in.  - I can't do that, sir.
好吧  强尼  我们不能让你亡命山中
Well, look, John, we can't have you running around
杀死友善百姓
wastir friendly civilians.
百姓没有友善的
There are no friendly civilians.
我是你的朋友  强尼
I'm your friend, Johnny.
越战时我和你生死与共  肝胆相照
I was there with you knee-deep in all that blood and guts.
我掩护你不止一次
I covered your ass more than once.
看爱我今生都要把你从麻烦中救出
Seems like bailir you out of trouble is gettir to be a lifetime job for me.
没有那个霸王警长  也就没有麻烦
There wouldn't be no trouble except for that king-shit cop.
我只想要吃一餐
All I wanted was something to eat,
他却一再逼我  长官
but the man kept pushing, sir.
你也逼人太甚  强尼
You did some pushing of your own, John,
是他们逼我流第一滴血  不是我
They drew first blood, not me.
强尼  让我去带你离开那里
Look, Johnny, let me come in and get you the hell out of there.
是他们逼我流第一滴血
They drew first blood.
蓝波  你仍然听得见我吗?
Rambo, are you still reading me?
请回答!  连长呼叫乌鸦
Covey Leader to Raven, Rambo, acknowledge.
他完了  上校!
He's all finished, Colonel
我们找出他的位置
We've got a real good fix on him, though.
天一亮我就带所有人上那山脉
Come first light, I'm gonna put every man I got up on that ridge,
然后我以我的方法抓他
Then we'll get him my way,
我要你横越这座山
All right, look down. I want you to stretch the skirmish
设下前哨线
line right across this ridge.
该死!  该死!
Goddamn it, Goddamn it.
快!  快走!
Come on! Move it!
我们追
Let's go,
这小子有枪吗?
Hey, this guy got a gun?
小心脚步
Watch your step,
那是什么?  那是什么?
What was that? What was that?
他走的哪条路?
Which way did he go?
翻过去  翻过去
Toss it across. Toss it,
爸爸...
Pa! Pa! Pa!
- 那里有个人  - 什么事?
- There's a guy over there!  - What happened, son?
- 我看到他了  在那边  - 我去抓他
- I see him! Over there!  - I' II get him!
别开枪  冷静
Don't shoot! Cool down!
这边!  我们走
This way! Let's go!
他在那边  快
There he is! Come on!
我们打中他了!
Now we got him!
我知道他在那里  仔细听好
Yes, Yes, I know exactly where it is. Listen to me very carefully,
用你所有的人包围那里但别进去
Surround the area with every man you've got, but don't move in.
我没到之前  什么也别做
I repeat, don't move in, In fact, don't do anything 'til I get there,
别开枪我不要死的  我要活的
And no shooting. I don't want him dead. I want him alive.
爬下!
Get down!
继续开枪!
Keep firing!
快!  开枪!
Come on, guys, Shoot!
快点
Come on!
你们真了不起
Oh, you guys are great,
- 你还好吗  史提夫  - 有!
- All right, Steve?  - Yo?
我要你和布鲁抄到矿坑前面
I want you and Bruce, head around these trees, go to the front of that mine,
去你的  克林顿  我才不去  门都没有
Screw that, Clinton, I ain't goir up there, No way,
- 雷门  - 什么?
- Raymond?  - What?
- 我要你进矿坑  - 我才不
- I want you to go into that mine.  - Oh, not me,
这话什么意思?
What do you mean, "not me"?
这是我的兼差  我不是来送命的
Look, I do this part-time, I didn't come to get killed.
他可能正在里面等我们
He's probably in there just waitir for us.
你有什么毛病  克林顿?
What's wrong with you, Clinton?
蓝波  我是摩根中尉国民军连长
All right, Rambo? This is Lieutenant Clinton Morgen, National Guard leader,
我给你三十秒出来
Now, I'm giving you just three-zero seconds to come on out!
火箭筒在谁手上?
Who's got the rocket launcher?
- 我  - 过来  尔洛
- I do,  - Come here, Earl
很好  蓝波  这是你出来的最后机会
Great, Rambo, this is your last chance to come out.
也许我们应该等
Maybe we should wait,
尔洛  这坏蛋是个杀手
Earl, this creep is a killer,
何况  是我指挥  我说要炸死他
Besides, I' m in charge, and I say we blow it up.
发射它!  先让我离远一点
Now fire that thing, Just let me get out of the way first,
给他一根雪茄  正中目标!
Give that man a cigar! Bull 's-eye!
- 他们在那里?  - 往山上走约五百码
- Where the hell are they?  - Up the hill about 500 yards,
走近点  象吉马一样
Move in a little closer, just like Iwo Jima,
我不敢相信  白痴!
I don't believe it. Idiots!
别动  好了
Steady, Got it,
- 再给福兵照一张  - 福兵?
- All right, Nick. One more for Soldier of Fortune. - Soldier of Fortune?
可恶!  你们以为这是什么?  马戏班?
Damn it! What the hell do you think this is? Some kind of a circus?
滚开!
Get the hell out of here!
克林顿  天啊!
Clinton, Jesus.
你没听见吗?  我叫你们等我来
Didrt you get the word? I told you people to wait until I got up here!
他在象我们射击  威尔  我不愿冒险
He was shooting at us, Will, Come on, I wasrt taking any chances,
天啊  乱七八糟
Christ, what a mess,
马上掘出他的尸体
We're gonna have to dig his body out of there right away,
推土机上不来  你必须找人掘出他
You can't get a dozer up here, You'll have to find somebody to dig him out.
是你弄的一团糟  克林顿  你来清理
It's your mess, Clinton, You clean it up,
威尔  别这样  我明天必须回药房
Will, come on! I gotta be back at the drugstore tomorrow,
你最好立刻开始动手  克林顿!
Then you better get started right away, Clinton!
可恶
Shit!
被一群周末战士埋葬
Buried in a hole by a bunch of goddamn weekend warriors.
你不是说他是你训练过最优秀的
I thought you said he was the best you ever trained,
他当时是很特别的
However he may have ended up, there was a time when he was very special
特别个屁  只是另一个违法流浪汉
Special, my ass, He's just another drifter that broke the law,
罪名是流浪罪?
Vagrancy, wasn't it?
刻在阿灵顿公墓他的墓碑很好吧
That's gonna look real good on his gravestone at Arlington,
这是赢得国会勋章的蓝波
"Here lies John Rambo, winner of the Congressional Medal of Honor,
从敌后无数任务中生还
survivor of countless incursions behind enemy lines,
在美国因流浪而被杀死
killed for vagrancy in jerkwarter, U.S.A."
少跟我胡说这些  崔普曼
Now don't give me any of that crap, Trautman.
你以为只有他在越南吃过苦头
You think Rambo was the only guy who had a tough time in Vietnam?
他杀了警察
He killed a police officer for Christ sake!
他没杀光你们算你们走运
You' re goddamn lucky he didn't kill all of ya.
这个人  他带着忠告来这里
This character, he comes waltzing in here full of all kinds of good advice.
像是我们该如何放这个疯子走
On how we should let the goddamn maniac go loose so we can save our own asses!
这样我们才能保命  上校  我们保命了
We saved our asses, Colonel,
也没让他逃走  最优秀的人输了
and we didn't let him go loose! The best man lost!
他却不满意!
And he doesn't like it!
你好吗  威尔?
How ya doir, Will?
我的电话全挡掉
Hold my calls
上校?
Colonel?
坐吧!
Have a seat,
小姐  请再做次好吗?
Oh, miss, would you do this again, please?
- 警长  - 给我的朋友...
- Hi, sheriff. - And for my friend,
给我个野火鸡牌
Give me a shooter. Wild Turkey,
我有点过分  我想道歉
Look, if I was out of line before, well, I just want to apologize.
现在那没差别了  对吧?
None of that makes much difference now, does it?
我想没有  我想...
Nah, I guess not, I suppose,
我也不知道  我只是觉得
I don't know, I just feel.
好像你是作弊而得胜?
Like you were cheated out of your chance,
我想要宰那小子
I wanted to kill that kid,
非常想  我可以感觉得到
I wanted to kill him so bad I could taste it,
戴着那徽章不好做吧?
Doesn't sit well with that badge, hmm?
有时你会很困惑
It can get confusing sometimes.
你得相信  在越南时
In Vietnam, you can bet that
我和蓝波也很困惑  但是我们有命令
Rambo and I got pretty confused. But we had orders.
怀疑只有死路一条
When in doubt, kill.
那又怎样  与你无关  你是个平民
What the hell, you're a civilian,
你可以回家
You can go home
回到妻子身边回到房子小花园
to your wife and your house and your little flower garden,
你没有想透那些事的压力
You're under no pressure to figure all this out.
你呢?  上校  你从这些事想透什么?
What about you, Colonel? What did you figure out from all of this, huh?
若你是我  他进本镇你会怎么做?
What would you have done with him if he came in?
拥抱热吻他?
Would you wrap your arms around him,
还是干掉他?
give him a big, sloppy kiss? Or would you have blown his brains out?
我要面对他才能回答这问题
I couldn't answer that until I met him face-to-face.
是的
Yeah.
就是这么回事
Well, there it is.
只是你没机会知道了
It's just as well we never got a chance to find out.
开车
Drive.
别看我  看路
Don't look at me, look at the road.
车祸就是这么发生的
That's how accidents happen.
- 你叫什么名字?  - 卡特劳勃
- What's your name?  - Cathcan't, Robert A,
- 车后面装了什么  劳勃?  - M16步枪
- All right, what do ya got in the back, Robert A?  - M16.
好  劳勃  下车去
Okay, Robert A, get outta the truck.
拜托  我跟你无冤无仇  别
Oh, please, I got no beef with you. No!
下去!
Go on! Move! Go!
5个越共正开车向中部行驶
SP Car 1, Charlie 5 to central
声音开大点?
Want to turn that up?
我们还在三线联播?
Are we still on that three-way hookup?
提索警长的办公室
Sheriff Teasle' s office,
- 罗杰  - 还在尝试
- Roger. - Still working.
你有什么消息!  福安?
What's your story, Steamboat?
看来有人太快结案了  那个蓝波
Looks like somebody pulled the plug too soon. That Rambo guy
又逃脱了  可恶
is on the loose again. Shit.
罗杰  福安  这是猎人
Roger, Steamboat. This is Trapper.
我们在26号高速公路上设置路障
We're setting up roadblocks on Highway 26.
威尔  是蓝波  他还活着
Hey, Will, it's Rambo, He's still around,
天啊!  快离开  走啊!
Holy fuck! All right, get out there right away, Move!
怎么回事?
What the hell is goir on anyway?
- 小心点  - 要爆炸了
- Watch yourself!  - They're all gonna blow!
全体市民注意
Attention all civilians,
为自身安全  请立刻撤离街道
For your own safety, please evacuate the streets immediately.
待在室内直到接到进一步指示
Remain indoors until you receive further instructions.
重覆  这是紧急事件
I repeat, this is a police emergency.
请立刻撤离街道
Please evacuate the streets immediately.
我们发现了蓝波的尸体
We found Rambo's body.
事实上  他偷了军车  炸了加油站
As a matter of fact, it stole an Army truck, blew up a gas station,
那小子又复活了
The kid is resilient,
打消你现在的念头
Forget what you're thinking and clear out while you can.
还走得开之前快走
Get the fuck outta here.
你带着你的忠告一起滚出去
Take your advice with you.
下午我们谈话时你就知道他活着
When I talked to you earlier, you knew he was still alive, didn't you?
- 我怀疑  - 当然
- I suspected.  - Yeah, sure,
这就是你赖着不走的原因  你训练他
That's why you stuck around, You trained him.
你教他如何逃出那种洞穴
You taught him how to get out of places like that cave,
但他是逃不出这地方的
But he's not gonna get out of this place,
提索  你和你的人过去都对付不了他
Teasle, you and all your men couldn't handle him before,
你现在凭什么认为你能对付他?
What makes you think you can handle him now?
天知道他现在准备干什么
Because God knows what damage he's perpared to do.
你会死的  提索
You're gonna die, Teasle.
人都会死的
Everybody dies,
这屋内只有一个人有五成机会
There's only one man in this room that's got half a chance,
不因为我比他厉害
That's not because I'm better than he is.
是因为他信任我
It's because he trusts me.
我是他仅有最亲近的亲人
See, I' m the closest thing to family he has left.
也许这正是我所需的优势
That may be all the edge I need.
天啊!  你们这些人从那里来?
Jesus Christ, where do you people come from?
不不  这是我的镇  这是我的工作
No, No, this is my job, Trautman, This is my town,
我不会把它交给你或蓝波或是任何人
I'm not giving it up to you or to Rambo or to anybody else.
你别挡我的路
Now, you just stay the hell out of my way.
- 接近点  - 我不能  还是太热
- Get a little closer!  - I can't! It's too goddamn hot!
威尔  我是莱斯特  听见没有
Will, this is Lester. Do you copy? Over,
快  我们走
Come on, let's go!
威尔  我是莱斯特  听见没有
Will, this is Lester. Do you copy? Over,
听着  威尔  我们有严重问题  公路被切断了
Listen, Will, we got some serious problems. The highway's been cut off.
卡车在这里  但我们找不到尸体
The truck's out here, but we couldn't find the body.
重复  没尸体  全烧毁了
I repeat, no body. It's totally burned out.
布莱斯  把那些人赶开!
Preston, get those people outta here!
移到南边去!  退后!  退后!
Move 'em back to the south side. Move back! Move back!
听着  威尔  我们不知道
Listen, Will we don't know how many...
汽油槽里存有多少气体泵
gasoline reservoirs there are under those gas pumps.
- 你听到了吗?  - 我们这有个报道员
- Do you copy? Over.  - We got a reporter here.
普雷斯顿  把他们推开!  我不管他是谁!
Preston, push them back! I don't care who he is!
把他们分散开!  把卡车开到另一边!
Move them around! Get the trucks to the other side!
快  我们走!
Come on! Let's go!
威尔  你听到了吗?
Will, do you copy? Over.
可恶  可恶  可恶
Goddamn it! Goddamn it!
开枪  开枪  开枪
Go ahead, Go ahead,
- 开枪啊!  你这疯子  - 蓝波
- Go ahead, you crazy son of a bitch! Finish!  - Rambo!
别开枪  听我说  你没有机会
Rambo, don't do it! Listen to me, Rambo. You have no chance.
放下武器
So drop your weapon.
我要命令直升机  载你回布莱登堡
I'm gonna order the chopper in to fly you back to Bragg,
停火!
Hold your fire!
可恩  停火
Kern! Hold your fire.
停火  停火
Hold your fire. Hold your fire!
考虑一下你在做什么
Think about what you're doing,
这地方被团团围住  没有出路
The building's perimeter is covered, No exits.
外面将近二百人  M十六多得是
There are nearly 200 men out there and a lot of M16s.
你不择手段造成这场私人战争
You did everything to make this private war happen.
你造成的破坏够多了
You've done enough damage!
任务结束了  明白吗?
This mission is over, Rambo. Do you understand me?
任务已经结束了
This mission is over!
看看外面
Look at 'em out there,
看他们
Look at 'em!
若你现在不结束他们会杀了你
If you don't end this now, they're gonna kill you,
这是你想要的吗?
Is that what you want?
结束了  强尼  结束了
It's over, Johnny, It 's over!
什么都没结束!
Nothing is over! Nothing!
不像关开关那么容易
You just don't turn it off!
越战不是我的
It wasn't my war!
是你要求我参战  不是我要求你
You asked me, I didn't ask you!
我采取必要手段打胜
And I did what I had to do to win!
但别人却另生枝节  不让我们打胜
But somebody wouldn't let us win!
我回国  在机场遭遇愤怒群众
Then I come back to the world, and I see all those maggots at the airport.
指责我是杀婴孩的凶手等等胡言乱语!
protestir me, spittir, callir me 'Baby Killer' and all kinds of vile crap!
他们算什么?  竟来抗议我
Who are they to protest me, huh? Who are they?
除非他们曾是我  去过越南
Unless they've been me and been there
知道他们所骂的是什么
and know what they're yelling about!
那时代让大家都不好受  蓝波
It was a bad time for everyone, Rambo.
都是过去的事了  对你而言是
It's all in the past now, For you!
对我而言  平民生活什么都不是!
For me, civilian life is nothing!
在战场上我们有荣誉
In the field, we had a code of honor:
大家互相照顾掩护
You watch my back, I watch yours,
回到这里  什么也不是
Back here there's nothing!
你是全连仅剩的战士
You're the last of an elite group.
别落到这般下场
Don't end it like this.
在越南  我可以驾炮艇  开坦克车
Back there I could fly a gunship, I could drive a tank,
我负责上百万的装备
I was in charge of million-dollar equipment!
在这里我连停车的工作都找不到
Back here I can't even hold a job parking cars!
靠
Fuck it. Oh.
天啊!
Geez, Oh, God.
大家都到那里去了
Where is everybody?
我有个朋友  丹福斯
I had a friend, it was Danforth.
我是有这些好兄弟  伙计
I had all these guys, man.
在越南我们相依为命
Back there I had all these flaky guys who were my friends.
回到这里什么也没有
Back here there's nothing.
记得丹福斯吗?
Remember Danforth?
他穿着黑头巾
He wore this black headband.
我拿了他的一只颜色笔  上面写着: "如果找到了
I took one of his magic markers and it said, "If found.
寄到拉斯维加斯"  因为我们常谈那里
Mail us to Las Vegas", 'cause we were always talking about Vegas.
还有58年分红色雪佛来蓬车
And his fuckir car, this red '58 Chevy convertible.
他总是谈论着那车
He was talking about this car.
他说要开着它直到车轮掉下来
He said we were gonna cruise 'til the tires fall off,
在西贡市  有个小孩走来
We go in this bar in Saigon, and this kid comes up
带着擦靴箱  他说 擦靴吧!
carrying a shoe shine box. And he says, "Shine, please, Shine."
我说不要  乔伊说要擦
I said no. He kept askir, and Joey said yeah,
我去拿麦酒  箱中装了引线
And I went to get a couple beers, And the box is wired,
小孩打开箱子
And he opened up the box.
把乔伊尸首炸得到处都是
Fuckir blew his body all over the place,
到处分散
And he's layir there, He's fuckir screamir,
我身上都是碎尸
There's pieces of him all over me, Just... like this.
我试图把碎尸拉下来
And I'm tryir to pull him off,
我朋友的身体粘的我全身都是
my friend that's all over me!
血与其他的融在一起  我想把他拼回来!
I've got blood and everything. I'm tryir to hold him together.
我想把他拼回来!  但是老是不成功!
I'm puttir the guy's fuckir insides keep comir out!
我找人帮忙  可没人帮忙!
And nobody would help! Nobody would help!
我听到乔伊说  我要回家
He's sayir, "I wanna go home, I wanna go home."
他一直叫我名字说  我要回家  强尼
He keeps callir my name. "I wanna go home, Johnny.
我要开雪佛来车
I wanna drive my Chevy."
我说  不行  我找不到你的腿
I said, "Why I can't find your fuckir legs.
我找不到你的腿
I can't find your legs.
我忘不了
I can't get it out of my head.
七年了  每一天都想到
I dream it seven years. Every day I have this.
有时我醒来  不知身在何处
Sometimes I wake up, I don't know where I am.
我不跟任何人说话
I don't talk to anybody.
有时一天
Sometimes a day.
有时一星期
Sometimes a week.
我忘不了
I can't put it out of my mind.
靠
Fuck it.